Dear Bante, I understand the interest in
freedom from suffering, but to aim for
destroying rebirth entirely seems
awfully extreme. Is the answer really to
just make myself stop existing? That
seems unrelated to suffering.
Well, no. It's not your choice to stop
existing. Even if you desire that as
Buddha talked about the one of the ways
of being is to crave against being.
So yeah, you certainly can't just desire
to stop existing and on that account
alone stop existing. You have to
essentially your existence has
conditions greater aversion and delusion
craving. And the same conditions that
lead you to exist are the conditions
that lead you to suffer.
So existence doesn't mean like your
kind of circumstantial presence
in the world.
Cuz if that were the case, then Anaran
wouldn't be able to be alive and have
given up existence.
Existence is determined by craving.
So yeah, if you want to be free from
suffering, you want to be free from
craving. And if you want to be free from
craving, you're freeing yourself from
the conditions for existence.
>> But then why would we call it existence
if you could still exist and be free
from existence?
>> Well, because that's how fundamental it
is. Like it's not that you're
it's not that you kind of
when you do certain things
pollution arises.
Your entire being conscious
the way it occurs now is polluted. In
other words, your entire existence the
way it is now is polluted.
Like even when it's in the most pristine
and kind of seemingly passive state,
it has all the same wrong implications
that make it possible for you to engage
in the course pollutions.
So
that's why you don't as as the Buddha
said there is no um point where craving
for being began where the pollution
began and then afterwards like there's
no point where there wasn't pollution
and then pollution arose.
The entire time it's been there.
you basically just have either
confirmations coarse confirmations of it
or not so coarse confirmations of it. So
that's why
it's that's why the Buddha talked about
it as existence so that you get a sense
of how broad the problem is and you
don't think that by preventing specific
things you're fixing the problem.
>> So then it's really it's not really
existence or you get a new existence. Uh
well, you certainly can't
like that's why you have stages of
training. You can't go from existing to not
You can't go from existing to not
existing. The only thing you can do is
refine the way that you exist.
Up until that way of existing is refined
enough for you to understand the
complete sensation of existence. So
initially you exist by breaking
precepts. You exist by actions of greed,
aversion, and delusion.
A more subtle state of existence is a
state where those actions are absent,
where they're given up. So you still
exist because you're still
well, you still have a sense of I am,
you still have a sense of ownership, you
are doing this restraint, you're doing
these um observance of the precepts and
so on, but factually it is a less coarse
state of existence.
than the opposite and to the same extent
is a state of less suffering because
existence and suffering are inseparable.
So that's a practical example of how you
could understand like oh yeah I could
still be alive I would still be um you
know able to talk speak all these things
yet my existence would have diminished
to the extent that I would have gone
from breaking precepts to not breaking
precepts as an actual internal practice
not just uh external compliance which
you could get to just by I don't know
being hospitalized. So you would refine
refining your existence would diminish
your suffering directly and you would
then see for yourself. Also, if this
existence that has now been refined,
if this would cease completely,
in other words, if there was no sense of
appropriation, no sense of
no sense of
duty, no sense of um obligation towards
any action whatsoever,
then I would be completely free from
suffering. And that's it. You don't like all the
And that's it. You don't like all the
other considerations of what will happen
to me? How will that feel?
What do I have now that I have to
remove? What was before that made this came to
What was before that made this came to
be? All of those are what the Buddha
called um
so those are distraction distracting
considerations that will only keep you within being
that will only keep you within being
within suffering.
So
you don't there's absolutely no need to
even concern yourself with what will
happen afterwards. You can't even
imagine it because that's exactly why
it's called existence. Your present
state of trying to imagine what the
sensation of existence would be like is
within your current existence. So it's
polluted. So instead of trying to imagine what
So instead of trying to imagine what
it's like, you simply remove the
conditions for your existence now.
And then you will know whatever comes
after will not be able to be suffering
and that's all that matters.
>> So if that scares somebody still the
thought of ending existence
>> it is going to be feel like death like
it is.
>> So that's not a that's not because they
just misunderstand oh if I if I kind of
find out what it actually means just
conceptually then it won't be scary
anymore. It has to be scary.
>> Yeah. Oh, it it will be scary to the
extent that your existence is still
coarse. So for somebody who still holds
the coarse existence of sensual being,
it's like from very warm extremely warm
burning to just complete freezing cold.
So that's going to be the extent of the
contrast. If on the other hand that that's why in
If on the other hand that that's why in
fact the Buddha said when he would teach
the dharma to people who would be very
far on that extreme for them it would
feel like death like they would be
pulling their hairs out in in despair
recognizing the extent of this of that
which for them would be annihilation.
And then if your being is has been
refined then it would be going from lukewarm to
then it would be going from lukewarm to
freezing or from already pretty cold to
freezing. So it won't feel like that
kind of precipice that you're that
you're throwing yourself into.
>> You have less to lose.
>> Yeah. Exactly. So and that's the whole
point like you are going to lose it
anyway. Like when you think about death, you get
Like when you think about death, you get
pretty much that same sense of precipice
that you would get if you thought about
fully giving up your being.
So you are going to have to go through
that anyway.
And the problem is you will go through
it once but then you will reacquire
things that you will lose again as
happens in this life. like you build
your whole career, build your whole uh
lifestyle around certain things, you
lose them entirely. And you could have
just thought, oh, rather than repeating
this again, let me just not build this
tower that will fall. No, but you don't
do that. You just build it up again and
then it falls again. So
that's the distinction like you have no
choice but to lose your being
but but to but to undergo that suffering
that that loss of all that you have
appropriated. It's just a question of whether you do
It's just a question of whether you do
it as a practice that will then free you
from that entirely like that you will
not take up things again
or whether you just keep
gaining and losing gaining and losing
gaining and losing indefinitely.
And that's what actual rebirth is. It's
not the uh like it's not just the
physical manifestation of a being or
something. That's the result of them
as as this is to say taking up
appropriating the sense spaces,
appropriating the aggregates.
That's why they're physically born, not
the other way around that you're
physically born and then this
appropriation happens.
Because see for example
when you think about
what makes you suffer
like do you suffer only when
let's let's take material possessions
which is the most relatable example like
do you suffer only when you actually
lose things
or does the fact that you have to
protect them
already imply suffering
and actually you realize
the reason why you would suffer when you
when you would lose them is because
you're trying to protect them.
So that comes first. If you were not
trying to protect them,
even if you lost them, you wouldn't
suffer. So that need to protect is what your
So that need to protect is what your
being is and that's what your suffering
is. even if you're not doing anything to
protect them so to speak
>> the internal need to do so is what the
being is. So that's how you realize oh
so being is what is suffering not just
the things that happened within being.
So even if you if even if you never lost
anything for a million years, the fact
that you still need to protect
which is what your existence is, that is
the fundamental suffering.
Whereas if you were to lose everything
every single day or like gain and lose
things every single day, you wouldn't be
suffering because there would be no
being there.
So, should I just
regularly switch out all my things?
>> Well, that's that's exactly the point of
that's what people would think like if I
just move from place to place, from
monastery to monastery as monks, um
change my habits,
don't don't hold on to the same things.
I am not clinging to being I'm not
developing appropriation.
But no, it's like the fundamental
appropriation is towards your own body,
towards your own senses, towards your
own feelings.
That's the one that everything else
flows out from.
So, ask yourself,
ask yourself,
is there any tendency for me to try to
protect what I feel
as if I have an entitlement in that
regard? So that's the being that you have to
So that's the being that you have to
abandon. And if switching things out is
being done for that purpose, then you're
actually making your being worse.
>> Also, you probably wouldn't be switching
out the habit of switching things out.
>> Yeah, of course. Like that's giving you
some kind of gratification
which you're protecting. So that's your
being. And that might be one of the only
things that you're dependent on,
especially if you're a monk and that's
your lifestyle. It would eventually
become the one thing like it's when like
when that monk uh when the Buddha asked
that wanderer who says um who said
nothing pleases him and then the Buddha
said well that is the thing that pleases
you like you might have given up
everything else but your the uh need to
protect that feeling of gratification
that you get is now uh condensed in this
one thing.
So you you don't want to be switching
things around.
You want to be training yourself out of
the entire principle.
And that's what actual for example um
samadei and janna is. Many people think
of it as a kind of um replacement of
your need for enjoyment, your need for
gratification, a better way of
satisfying that hunger.
But it's the sensation of that hunger
which the sutas explicitly state it's
the abandonment of that entire principle
of needing gratification
that would then lead you to peace. Like
again even if you think about it
practically when are you peaceful? When
you when you have been promised that
nobody will steal your car or when you
don't have a car to protect in the first
place or when you have a car but you
don't need to protect it.
So that's the purification of